<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tandem bona causa triumphet, or, Scotlands late misery bewailed, and the honour and loyalty of this ancient kingdom, asserted in a sermon preached before His Majesties High Commissioner, and the Honourable Parliament of the kingdom of Scotland, at Edinburgh the 17 day of February, 1661 / by Mr. John Paterson, Minister of the Gospel at Aberdene.</title>
            <author>Paterson, John, 1604?-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55727</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P328</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17861</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11864428</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11864428</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50069</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55727)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50069)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 503:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tandem bona causa triumphet, or, Scotlands late misery bewailed, and the honour and loyalty of this ancient kingdom, asserted in a sermon preached before His Majesties High Commissioner, and the Honourable Parliament of the kingdom of Scotland, at Edinburgh the 17 day of February, 1661 / by Mr. John Paterson, Minister of the Gospel at Aberdene.</title>
                  <author>Paterson, John, 1604?-1679.</author>
                  <author>Paradise, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed at Edinburgh, and reprinted at London for James Thrale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing attributes this edition of the text to John Paradise; the edition of 1681 (probably the original), he assigns to John Paterson.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezekiel VII, 23 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, Scottish --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  17th century --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50069:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Tandem bona cauſa Triumphat. OR SCOTLANDS Late miſery bewailed; and the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> of this <hi>Antient</hi> KINGDOM, Aſſerted in a SERMON, Preached before His Majeſties High Commiſſioner, and the Honourable Parliament of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland.</hi> At <hi>Edinburgh</hi> the 17. day of <hi>February.</hi> 1661.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>JOHN PATERSON,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>ABERDENE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezekiel 7.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Make a Chain: for the land is full of bloody crimes, and the city is full of violence.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and Reprinted at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>James Thrale,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50069:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50069:2"/>
            <head>TO THE TRUELY NOBLE, Valorous and Famous LORD, The Earl of MIDLETON, Lord <hi>Clairmont</hi> and <hi>Fettercairn,</hi> His Majeſties High Commiſſioner for <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your GRACE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſimple ſtrain of the following <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> being adorned with no Flowers of <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi> no entiſements of humane <hi>Eloquence,</hi> nor ſwelled with Citations of Humane <hi>Writers, Antient,</hi> or <hi>Modern,</hi> ſpeaketh it out ſufficiently to all men of <hi>Spirit</hi> or <hi>Candor,</hi> that it is not <hi>Pride</hi> or <hi>Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that hath put it to the <hi>Preſſe;</hi> but the true reaſon wherefore it appeareth to the <hi>World</hi> ſo publickely, is to prevent and obſtruct the <hi>Miſrepreſentations</hi> of other, who
<pb facs="tcp:50069:3"/>having taken it by ſwift writing when it was delivered, may perchance wrong the <hi>Authour,</hi> either from <hi>miſtake</hi> or <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice.</hi> When it cometh abroad, I know it will meet with ſuch <hi>entertainment,</hi> as Papers of a more Elaborate and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious <hi>compoſure</hi> have done before. Who knoweth not, <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> to be a reſtleſſe <hi>Wretch,</hi> like a filthy <hi>Flie</hi> which ſeeketh all the body over for a <hi>Soar,</hi> and when ſhe cannot find one, ſhe maketh one? I ſhould wiſh to be free of ſuch <hi>Waſps;</hi> but ſince it is not probable, that it can be ſo, in this <hi>Conjuncture</hi> of <hi>Affairs</hi> and <hi>bleſſed Revolution,</hi> when mens <hi>ſpirits</hi> are not to be ſeen in their <hi>Faces,</hi> nor their <hi>Loyalty</hi> to be known by their <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick:</hi> I have adventured upon thoſe mens <hi>Criticiſms,</hi> to whom I neither ſtand nor fall. Let none think that I preſume in ſuch a plain <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> to teach the Learned, who are more knowing nor myſelf; yet the <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and ſuch as have fleeted hither till, upon the ſurface of <hi>Buſineſſes,</hi> may be brought to ſome ſerious <hi>conſideration,</hi> how deeply the <hi>Stability</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> of a <hi>Nation,</hi> which is truely <hi>MONARCHICAL</hi> is founded: and if I ſhall meet with a cloud of <hi>Obloquie, Malice,</hi> and <hi>Prejudice,</hi> for ſpeaking the truth in <hi>freedom</hi> and <hi>ſoberneſſe,</hi> Who ſhall ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me, but your <hi>GRACE</hi> and the High Court of <hi>PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT,</hi> at whoſe command I did preach? Therefore let it not offend your <hi>GRACE,</hi> that I have preſumed to affix your Name to ſuch a worthleſſe <hi>Piece,</hi> and offered it to your Judicious View and Cenſure: I have no excuſe, but my reall <hi>Reſpects</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> to your <hi>GRACE</hi> (to whom I am ſo much engaged for your ſo many undeſerved <hi>Civilities,</hi>) which have imboldened me to lay it down at your feet, and to let the <hi>World</hi> ſee it under your <hi>GRACES Patrociny.</hi> If I know my ſelf well, I account <hi>Flattery</hi> below me; but I know it is <hi>Juſtice</hi> to ſpeak the truth of all men, and eſpecially of thoſe whom God hath made the <hi>Shields</hi> of the <hi>Earth:</hi> Yet your <hi>GRACES</hi> innate <hi>Modeſty</hi> maketh me ſparing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall onely ſay this, that the <hi>LORD</hi> hath made your <hi>GRACE</hi> a poliſhed ſhaft in his own hand under the <hi>KING'S MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY,</hi> to raiſe up
<pb facs="tcp:50069:3"/>a poor ſinking <hi>Land</hi> from the deep waters of <hi>Tyranny, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, Trouble</hi> and <hi>Anarchy:</hi> to vindicate the Honor of this Ancient <hi>NATION,</hi> over which ſome <hi>Unnaturall</hi> men had ſtretched a black Cloud of <hi>Diſloyalty</hi> and <hi>Reproach,</hi> to Aſſart and Reſtore His <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> juſt <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive:</hi> to ſweep down mdny <hi>Spiders Webs,</hi> which the <hi>Iniquity</hi> of the late <hi>Times</hi> had woven, to the great <hi>offence</hi> of <hi>GOD, Scandall</hi> of the Proteſtant <hi>Religion,</hi> to the ſad <hi>Affliction</hi> and bearing down of His <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> moſt <hi>Loyal</hi> and <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subjects.</hi> The <hi>LORD</hi> hath made your <hi>GRACE</hi> and this Noble Court of <hi>PARLIAMENT,</hi> eminently <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental</hi> to ſettle this long toſſed <hi>NATION,</hi> upon a ſolid <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> to break <hi>Yokes,</hi> and undo <hi>Heavy Burthens,</hi> and is ſhall be your <hi>Honor,</hi> and the <hi>Honor</hi> of this <hi>Noble</hi> and <hi>Loyal PARLIAMENT</hi> in all <hi>Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to come, to be called (under <hi>GOD,</hi> and the <hi>KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAJESTY</hi>) The <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parers</hi> of <hi>SCOTLANDS</hi> wofull <hi>Breach,</hi> and <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of our ſad <hi>Diſtempers.</hi> Go on as you have begun to act vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly and prudently for <hi>GOD,</hi> for <hi>RELIGION, KING, CHURCH</hi> and <hi>COUNTREY,</hi> and the Lord ſhall be with you. This ſhall be the daily Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your GRACES moſt humble and affectionate Servant, Mr. <hi>JOHN PATERSON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:50069:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50069:4"/>
            <head>TANDEM BONA CAUSA TRIUMPHAT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ezek. 7.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Make a chain; for the land is full of Bloody crimes, and the City is full of violence.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Mind (Godwilling) to ſpeak on this <hi>Text.</hi> Firſt, by way of <hi>Explication</hi> as it relateth to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and to their condition when the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> pend it. Secondly, By way of <hi>Application,</hi> to the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of this <hi>Kingdom,</hi> both as it was of late, as it is at preſent: and as I humbly conceive, it ought to be for the time coming.</p>
            <p>You may be pleaſed to take up the words into two main <hi>Points.</hi> Firſt, We have the <hi>Jews condition</hi> when <hi>Ezekiel</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered this ſpeech to them, and that is holden forth under the Emblem of a <hi>Chain,</hi> not a <hi>Chain</hi> of Gold, nor a <hi>Chain</hi> of Honor, but a <hi>Chain</hi> of Bondage and Captivity. Secon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, We have the cauſe wherefore a <hi>Chain</hi> was their lot, or wherefore they were given over to <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity,</hi> and that is their <hi>ſins,</hi> their overſpreading <hi>iniquity,</hi> the Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical <hi>wickedneſs</hi> which had overflowed both <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, For the land is full of bloody crimes, and the City is full of violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:50069:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Point</hi> I. We have the <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> at this time, and that was, <hi>wofull, miſerable</hi> and <hi>ſlaviſh,</hi> this is holden out under the Emblem of a <hi>Chain.</hi> The <hi>Septuagints</hi> in their Tranſlation of the Old Teſtament, render the word <hi>Trouble,</hi> the Vulgar Latin renders it <hi>Concluſion,</hi> or an <hi>end,</hi> make an <hi>end:</hi> But the Hebrew Word carrieth properly a <hi>Chain,</hi> it is that ſame word that is uſed, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 6.21. where there is mention made of <hi>Chains</hi> of Gold before the Oracle, and ſo do the <hi>Jewiſh Rabbies</hi> read it. Anent this Point of the <hi>Text,</hi> I mind (Godwilling) to hint at three <hi>particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What <hi>likeneſs</hi> or <hi>reſemblance</hi> there is betwixt a <hi>Chain,</hi> and the <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity</hi> of a Land. 2. I ſhall (God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing) ſpeak of the makers of this <hi>Chain, Make a chain,</hi> &amp;c. 3. Give you ſome <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes</hi> from this firſt branch of the <hi>Text,</hi> and proceed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity</hi> of a Nation, is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a <hi>Chain;</hi> becauſe as a chain of Iron, as an engine, that reſtraineth a man from his naturall <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:</hi> ſo <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity</hi> depriveth a <hi>Nation</hi> of their Civil and Eccleſiaſtick <hi>Liberty.</hi> A people that are under <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, Captivity,</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> may walk up and down the ſtreets, by a natural and animal <hi>motion;</hi> but as to any Civil or Publick <hi>Concernment,</hi> that Land is but in a <hi>Chain,</hi> they have no freedom to act, neither as <hi>Civil</hi> men, nor as <hi>Religious</hi> men: Such was the condition of the <hi>Jews,</hi> when <hi>Ezekiel</hi> did write this, they were in a <hi>Chain,</hi> fettered, deprived of their <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> and that both in reference to their <hi>Civil,</hi> and to their <hi>Church</hi> State. As for their civil capacity, they were ruled, overruled and tyrannized over, by <hi>Strangers</hi> and <hi>Conquerours:</hi> and for their Religious Liberty as Church Members, any thing they enjoyed that way, was but a ſhaddow of <hi>Liberty:</hi> As may be ſeen, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. by that Idol ſet up by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in the plain of <hi>Dura.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity</hi> of a Nation, is fitly compared to a <hi>Chain;</hi> becauſe to be bound in <hi>Chains</hi> of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, is a ſad and comfortleſs <hi>condition:</hi> Such is the <hi>condition</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50069:5"/>and <hi>ſtate</hi> of a <hi>Nation</hi> that is under <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> their <hi>condition</hi> is moſt ſad and lamentable, it is a very comfortleſs ſtate; ſuch was the <hi>Jews condition</hi> at this time, they were in <hi>Chains,</hi> in a very ſad and comfortleſs <hi>condition,</hi> Pſal. 137. <hi>When we ſat by the rivers of Babilon, there we wept, we hang'd our harps upon the willow trees.</hi> And <hi>Lament.</hi> 1. <hi>She weepeth ſore in the night, and her tears are on her cheeks, amongſt all her lovers ſhe hath none to comfort her, all her friends have dealt treacherouſly with her, Juda is gone into captivity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Captivity</hi> of a <hi>Nation</hi> is fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a <hi>Chain;</hi> becauſe as a <hi>Chain</hi> of Iron laid upon a <hi>Malefactor</hi> is a heavy burden to him, ſo that the poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot walk nor ſtir, even ſo a <hi>Land</hi> that is under <hi>cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity</hi> and <hi>bondage,</hi> hath a great weight on it, a weight that preſſeth it ſore down: This was the <hi>Jews condition</hi> at this time, their <hi>Chain</hi> was heavy enough. <hi>Lord, thou hath made our chain heavy,</hi> Lam. 3.7.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>captivity</hi> of a <hi>Nation</hi> is fitly compared to a <hi>chain,</hi> becauſe of <hi>reproach</hi> and <hi>diſgrace;</hi> for as it is a diſcredible and diſgracefull thing to be bound in <hi>chains</hi> and <hi>fetters</hi> of Iron; ſo a <hi>Land</hi> that is brought under <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> is in a diſgraceful and diſcredible <hi>condition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, The <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>captivity</hi> of a <hi>Nation</hi> is called a <hi>chain;</hi> becauſe, as poor <hi>malefactors</hi> that are bound in <hi>chains</hi> and <hi>fetters,</hi> ordinarily are the object of <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>deriſion,</hi> at leaſt to the <hi>raſcality,</hi> although any that hath true humanity in their breaſts, can pity the worſt of <hi>Malefactors,</hi> Even ſo a Nation in bondage and captivity, is but an object of <hi>ſcorn</hi> and <hi>deriſion</hi> to their enemies: So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. <hi>Let us have ſome of your Hebrew ſongs. We are a reproach to our neighbours,</hi> ſaith the Royal Pſalmiſt.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, The <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>captivity</hi> of a <hi>Nation</hi> is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a <hi>chain;</hi> becauſe, to be bound in <hi>chains</hi> of Iron; impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a purpoſe to keep the poor creature ſure, that he eſcape not: Even ſo theſe that maketh a people <hi>captive,</hi> they ſtudy to lay ſuch ſtrong <hi>Chains</hi> and <hi>Bonds</hi> on them, that they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50069:6"/>may never be able to eſcape out of their <hi>bondage,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their former <hi>liberty:</hi> there is no human policy that they leave uneſſayed to keep that people faſt in their <hi>bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> and <hi>ſlavery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, The <hi>Captivity</hi> and <hi>Bondage</hi> of a Nation, is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a <hi>Chain;</hi> becauſe as theſe who keep <hi>Malefactors</hi> in <hi>Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> have a further purpoſe againſt them, to bring them to <hi>Tryal</hi> and <hi>Execution:</hi> Even ſo theſe who Conquers a Land, and brings it under <hi>Bondage,</hi> they have ſtill ſome further purpoſe to bring that people more and more under <hi>Slavery;</hi> for it is not ordinary for thoſe who leadeth a <hi>Nation captive,</hi> and mindeth to fix their <hi>Tyrannie,</hi> to do their worſt at firſt, except it be in the heat and fury of <hi>Battel,</hi> but to wreath on the yoke piece and piece, till they render them abſolutely incapable of a revolt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond particular propoſed on the firſt <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> was, Who were the <hi>makers</hi> of this <hi>chain, Make a chain,</hi> &amp;c. As to this I ſay, There were ſeveral <hi>Makers</hi> of this <hi>Chain,</hi> every one in their own <hi>Line</hi> and <hi>Conſideration.</hi> Firſt, <hi>God</hi> made this <hi>Chain,</hi> as the <hi>Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Great Judge</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves had a very eminent hand in making this <hi>Chain,</hi> by their ſins and abominations. Thirdly, The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> had ſome hand in making of it, in a Miniſterial ſenſe. Fourthly, The <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonians</hi> had an <hi>Immediat</hi> hand in making it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay that <hi>God</hi> made this <hi>Chain:</hi> It was the <hi>Lord</hi> that brought this ſad <hi>captivity</hi> and <hi>bondage</hi> upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> it was the <hi>Lord</hi> that ſent them <hi>captive</hi> to <hi>Babylon,</hi> it was he that brought up that Northern Army againſt them, he raiſed up the ſpirit of that haſty and furious <hi>Nation</hi> againſt his own people, and this he did out of his <hi>Soveraignty</hi> and <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The <hi>Jows</hi> themſelves had an eminent hand in making this <hi>chain,</hi> by their <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>abominations,</hi> by provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Holy one of Iſrael to anger:</hi> and I am apt enough to believe, that even ſeveral <hi>unnatural</hi> and <hi>treacherous</hi> men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> had a hand in making this <hi>chain,</hi> by their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50069:6"/>treacherous compliance with the <hi>Babylonians;</hi> for you ſhall read in few Stories, that ever a <hi>Nation</hi> or <hi>Kingdom</hi> was inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and conquered by an <hi>Enemy,</hi> and brought under a <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>Bondage;</hi> but alwaies ſome unnatural <hi>Monſters,</hi> ſome <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical, Temporizing, Self-ſeeking Traitors,</hi> have compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Enemy, I mean, complied actively and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and other Prophets, had ſome kind of hand in making this <hi>Chain;</hi> for you ſee the command here is given to <hi>Ezekiel, Make a chain.</hi> It is on this account, that the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have hewed them by my Prophets:</hi> And, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.10, <hi>See, I have ſet thee this day over the Nations, and over the Kingdoms, to root out, and to pull down, and to deſtroy.</hi> Now <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and other Prophets, had a hand in making this <hi>Chain.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Praedicendo,</hi> by foretelling the <hi>Jews</hi> captivity, before it came, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord; behold I frame evil againſt you.</hi> Secondly, It may be ſaid in ſome ſenſe, that <hi>Ezekiel</hi> and other Prophets, had a hand in making this <hi>Chain, Comminando,</hi> by threatning it as a ſad imminent <hi>Judgment.</hi> And, Thirdly, by making the hearts of the people <hi>Fat,</hi> through their own corruption, and obſtinacy. <hi>Go, make the heart of this people Fat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> and <hi>Babylonians,</hi> had an imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat hand in making this <hi>Chain,</hi> as the <hi>Inſtruments of GOD,</hi> and the <hi>Executioners</hi> of his <hi>wrath</hi> upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that in theſe <hi>Conſiderations.</hi> 1 They projected this <hi>Chain,</hi> they did in their ſecret <hi>Counſels</hi> and <hi>Deſigns,</hi> plot and contrive, to bring the <hi>Jews</hi> under <hi>Bondage.</hi> 2. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> had an immediat hand in making this <hi>Chain,</hi> by an actual <hi>Invaſion:</hi> they not only plotted, and deſigned to invade the <hi>Jews,</hi> but they did actually invade them. 3. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> had an immediat hand in making this <hi>Chain</hi> for the <hi>Jews,</hi> by <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming</hi> and <hi>Conquering</hi> them. 4. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> had an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediat hand in making this <hi>Chain,</hi> by leading many of the <hi>Jews</hi> captive to <hi>Babylon:</hi> in making them <hi>Exyles</hi> from their native <hi>Countrey.</hi> 5. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> had an immediat hand
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50069:7"/>in making this <hi>Chain</hi> for the <hi>Jews,</hi> by <hi>Garriſoning</hi> many parts of their <hi>Countrey.</hi> 6. By appointing of <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors</hi> over them that were for the moſt part <hi>Strangers.</hi> 7. By laying on them ſad <hi>Impoſitions</hi> and <hi>Taxations.</hi> And thus you may ſee who made this <hi>Chain</hi> to the <hi>Jews: GOD</hi> made it as a moſt juſt <hi>Judge,</hi> to puniſh the <hi>Jews,</hi> for the abuſe of their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and for their other <hi>Sins:</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> made it as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactors:</hi> the <hi>Prophet</hi> made it as the <hi>LORDS Meſſenger:</hi> the <hi>Babylonians</hi> made it, as the <hi>LORDS Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> Now before I paſs this firſt branch of the <hi>Text, Make a chain,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. That the LORDS own people may meet with a <hi>Chain:</hi> they may be brought under ſad <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>captivity</hi> for their <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>iniquities.</hi> This was the lote of the <hi>Jews</hi> many times: they were in <hi>Chains</hi> and <hi>Bondage</hi> in <hi>Egypt:</hi> in <hi>Chains</hi> by <hi>Tigloth-Pileſer:</hi> made <hi>captives</hi> by <hi>Salmanezer:</hi> by <hi>Senacherib:</hi> by the Captains of the Hoſt of the King of <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> who carried <hi>Mannaſſeh</hi> captive to <hi>Babylon.</hi> I ſay, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in whom God hath a ſpecial intereſt, may meet with a <hi>Chain:</hi> they may be brought under ſad <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity,</hi> like poor <hi>Malefactors,</hi> that are fettered in <hi>Chains</hi> of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron; ſo that <hi>Turkiſh Argument,</hi> from ſucceſs or not ſucceſs to juſtify or condemn a <hi>Procedor,</hi> is ill Divinity: This ſandy argument was too much plyed in our late <hi>Troubles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. That who ſo ever be the immediat Inſtruments of the <hi>Chain</hi> of GODS people, God is the chief and principall <hi>Author</hi> thereof himſelf: It is the LORD who commands to make this <hi>Chain, Make a chain,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, it is GOD in his <hi>Soveraignty, Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> that maketh <hi>Chains</hi> for a <hi>Land:</hi> who ever be the immediat Inſtruments of their <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>captivity;</hi> And therefore it is their duty to look beyond Inſtruments, to a far higher hand, than creatures are: ſo did <hi>Job,</hi> and ſo did <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Shimei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. That before GOD bring a judgment upon a <hi>Land</hi> or <hi>Family;</hi> he giveth them ſome warning before hand: ſome time to repent and eſcape the <hi>wrath</hi> threatened: So
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50069:7"/>dealt GOD with the old <hi>World:</hi> ſo with the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Matth.</hi> 22. But I come to the ſecond <hi>branch</hi> of the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Point</hi> II. Wherein we have ſet down the cauſe wherefore this <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>captivity</hi> and <hi>bondage</hi> was made for the <hi>Jews,</hi> and wreathed about their <hi>Necks,</hi> and that was for their <hi>ſins</hi> and <hi>iniquity (For the land is full of bloody crimes, and the city is full of violence.)</hi> Here let us conſider theſe <hi>things.</hi> 1. The particular <hi>ſins</hi> challenged upon the <hi>Jews, Blood</hi> and <hi>Violence.</hi> 2. The <hi>hainouſneſs</hi> of theſe ſins, they are not ordinary <hi>ſins,</hi> but <hi>crimes</hi> and <hi>bloody crimes.</hi> 3. The <hi>univerſality</hi> or the <hi>overſpreading</hi> of theſe <hi>ſins,</hi> it was both <hi>Country and City</hi> that was infected with them. 4. The height of theſe <hi>ſins,</hi> the <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>City</hi> was filled with them, their ſins were come to a great height.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The particular <hi>ſins</hi> wherewith the LORD by his <hi>Prophet</hi> challengeth the <hi>Jews,</hi> are wrapt up in two <hi>words,</hi> which are very large and comprehenſive, <hi>Bloody crimes and violence.</hi> I ſhall firſt <hi>(God willing)</hi> open theſe two words, <hi>Bloody crimes</hi> and <hi>violence.</hi> Secondly, Shew you how many wayes a <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>blood,</hi> or with <hi>bloody crimes.</hi> Thirdly, How many wayes a <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>violence.</hi> Then I ſhall come <hi>(God willing)</hi> to apply the whole <hi>Text</hi> to this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>two words</hi> which the <hi>Prophet</hi> maketh uſe of here, to expreſs the ſins of the <hi>Jews,</hi> are <hi>Bloody crimes</hi> and <hi>violence,</hi> Some <hi>Writers</hi> take this expreſſion, <hi>bloody crimes,</hi> in a general ſenſe, for all hainous and greivous ſins whatſoever; eſpecially for capital and criminal ſins, deſerving death by the judicial <hi>Law:</hi> Such as <hi>Idolatry, Deut.</hi> 13. <hi>Blaſphemy, Lev.</hi> 24. <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft</hi> and <hi>Sorcery, Beaſtiality, Sodomy,</hi> Lev. 20 <hi>Rapes,</hi> Deut, 22. I deny not but the word may bear this large ſenſe; but I take it more ſtrintly for ſhedding of <hi>Innocent blood,</hi> and that by them that had the Power in their hand, and pretended to do <hi>Juſtice:</hi> ſome render it the Judgements of <hi>Blood:</hi> did not <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> make the ſtreets of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to ſwim with <hi>Blood,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50069:8"/>with Innocent <hi>Blood;</hi> as may be cleared from <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1. and 59. <hi>Your hands are full of Blood.</hi> And for the word <hi>Violence,</hi> by it we are to underſtand every thing that is contrary to <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to <hi>Equity,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> Eſpecially <hi>Robery</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> falſe, unrighteous, and unjuſt <hi>Dealing. Zeph.</hi> 3. <hi>Wo to her that is Filthy and Polluted, Wo to the oppreſſing City: Her Princes within Her, are roaring Lions, Her Judges are evening Wolves: they ſuck the Blood of the Poor, they eat their Fleſh, and they gnaw their Bones.</hi> So is it <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. <hi>Caſt a mount againſt Jeruſalem, this is the City to be viſited; for ſhe is wholly Oppreſſion in the midſt of her, Violence and Spoil is heard in her Streets.</hi> Thus the two great <hi>National ſins,</hi> which brought this <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>Captivity</hi> on <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> was <hi>Innocent Blood, Injuſtice, Oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>Violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond particular on this branch of the <hi>Text,</hi> was, How many wayes a <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled, or filled with <hi>blood.</hi> I ſhall only name ſome of many. 1. By private <hi>man-ſlaughter,</hi> I mean occaſional <hi>ſlaughter.</hi> 2. By <hi>murther,</hi> or by lying in wait to kill. 3. By theſe damnable <hi>Duels,</hi> which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by all ſound <hi>Divines,</hi> and ſound <hi>Politicians,</hi> &amp; ought to be moſt ſeverely puniſhed, eſpecially in the <hi>Challengers.</hi> 4. A <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>blood,</hi> by an unjuſt and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>VVar.</hi> 5. By cruel and bloody <hi>Plots, Conſpiracies,</hi> and <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres:</hi> ſuch as that of <hi>Paris,</hi> where the blood of 30000. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> was ſhed at one time: So was <hi>Ireland</hi> defiled with <hi>blood,</hi> with the innocent <hi>blood</hi> of many thouſand <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Which horrible <hi>cruelty,</hi> ſome, yea, too many were not aſhamed to lay to our late murthered KING'S <hi>door,</hi> moſt falſely and unjuſtly; but that was not the firſt lye, which his implacable and treacherous <hi>Enemies</hi> invented, &amp; which evil mens <hi>Tongues</hi> ſounded out againſt him. Oh! to have branded ſuch a <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, Innocent</hi> KING, with ſuch <hi>damnable, bloody cruelty,</hi> how horrid a <hi>guiltineſſe</hi> was it before GOD. But, 6. A <hi>Land</hi> may be polluted with <hi>blood,</hi> by falſe and unjuſt <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> pronounced on the <hi>Bench,</hi> even that which ſhould be the Seat of <hi>Juſtice.</hi> Laſtly, A <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>blood,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50069:8"/>with innocent <hi>blood</hi> upon <hi>Scaffolds,</hi> when innocent and juſt <hi>Perſons,</hi> are moſt unjuſtly and cruelly <hi>Murthered</hi> and <hi>Butcher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> like <hi>Beaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third <hi>Particular</hi> on this Branch of the <hi>Text,</hi> was, How many wayes a <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>Violence,</hi> or with <hi>Injuſtice, Oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſſe.</hi> I ſhall only name ſome few.</p>
            <p>Firſt, A <hi>Land</hi> or <hi>City</hi> may be defiled, with <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> even in bargaining, in buying and ſelling, <hi>Lev.</hi> 25. <hi>When thou ſelleſt any thing to thy neighbour</hi> (and conſequently when thou buyeſt any thing from him) <hi>you ſhall not oppreſſe one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, A <hi>Land</hi> or <hi>City</hi> may be defiled with <hi>Violence,</hi> when that which is juſtly due to any <hi>Perſon,</hi> is unjuſtly, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, or falſely detained from them, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. <hi>Behold the hire of the labourers, who have reaped your harveſt, which is detained by you by fraud, cryeth.</hi> It is <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> and ſo is all <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſſe,</hi> Mal. 3. <hi>I will be a ſwift witneſſe againſt theſe who oppreſſe the hireling in his wages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, A <hi>Land</hi> or <hi>City</hi> may be defiled with <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Oppreſsion,</hi> when too heavy and inſupportable <hi>Bnrthens, Taxes</hi> and <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> are laid on it, which it cannot bear without <hi>ſighs</hi> and <hi>groans:</hi> and this may be not only the fault of the <hi>Supream Powers,</hi> but even of inferiour <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of a <hi>Land,</hi> by an unjuſt and unequal dividing, and laying on of publick <hi>Taxes</hi> and <hi>Burthens,</hi> when the poorer ſort of people are taxed and rated beyond, not only their power, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their due proportion, and the richer ſort ſpared: to take the burthen of the <hi>Rich,</hi> and to lay it on the <hi>Poor,</hi> is a horrible <hi>Violence</hi> in the ſight of JEHOVAH.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, A <hi>Land</hi> or <hi>City</hi> may be defiled with <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> by perverting or delaying of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> when the <hi>Poor,</hi> the <hi>Widow</hi> and the <hi>Fatherleſſe,</hi> are born down in <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> in their juſt and righteous <hi>Cauſe,</hi> by the Richer ſort, whether it be by <hi>Money, Friendſhip,</hi> or <hi>Money,</hi> Iſa. 1. <hi>Every one loveth gifts, and followeth rewards: they judge not the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50069:9"/>fatherleſſe, nor doth the cauſe of the widow come before them.</hi> To delay or pervert <hi>Juſtice,</hi> is horrible <hi>Iniquity</hi> and <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, A <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> by Ingroſſers and Monopolizers.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, A <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>Violence</hi> by <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> when people maketh a prey of holy things, of thoſe things which are devoted and conſecrated to GOD, to his <hi>Church,</hi> to the <hi>Poor,</hi> to <hi>Pious uſes:</hi> theſe are they who devour holy things, Pſal. 83. <hi>Let us take to our ſelves the houſes of God in poſſeſſion.</hi> Theſe are Sacrilegious Oppreſſors, and their ſin is Sacrilegious <hi>Violence:</hi> They deal with the Church as <hi>Dyoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> dealt with <hi>Iupiter Olympus,</hi> he took from that <hi>Idol</hi> a Garment of maſſie Gold, which <hi>Hero</hi> had dedicated of the Spoils of <hi>Carthage,</hi> ſaying, It was too heavy for <hi>Summer,</hi> and too cold for <hi>Winter,</hi> and put a Garment of VVool about the Statue, ſaying, This is fit for both ſeaſons of the year.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, A <hi>Land</hi> may be defiled with <hi>Violence,</hi> by impoſing and tyrannizing over mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and that is the ſaddeſt oppreſſion of all, when force and violence is done to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> (I mean) in point of mens judgement, when they are content to ſubmit and conform in their practiſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in things which are in themſelves, but meerly <hi>problema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> and <hi>diſputable,</hi> and which may be holden <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>contra,</hi> without any hazard or loſſe of <hi>Salvation,</hi> or of a good <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> matters where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nent Pious and Learned Orthodox <hi>Divines,</hi> are not agreed among themſelves. VVhen ſuch things are impoſed upon mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> as neceſſary and <hi>Fundamental Truths,</hi> this is horrible <hi>Violence.</hi> As to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality,</hi> or <hi>Overſpreading</hi> of theſe ſins amongſt the <hi>Iews,</hi> both <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>City</hi> were defiled with <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Violence:</hi> And as to the height of theſe <hi>Sins, The land is full of bloody crimes, and the city is full of violence:</hi> Time forceth me to paſſe theſe two Particulars.</p>
            <p>Now I come to apply the <hi>Text,</hi> and what I have ſaid on it in reference to the <hi>Iews,</hi> to this <hi>Land</hi> wherein we live. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50069:9"/>I ſhall apply it (God willing) in theſe <hi>Conſiderations.</hi> Firſt, What our <hi>condition</hi> was of late, we were in a <hi>chain</hi> under a baſe <hi>Bondage</hi> and <hi>Slavery.</hi> Secondly, Who were the <hi>makers</hi> of that <hi>chain.</hi> Thirdly, The <hi>cauſes</hi> wherefore GOD ſuffered us to come under ſuch a ſad <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>bondage.</hi> Fourthly, I ſhall in a word exhort all <hi>Ranks</hi> to Repentance, for our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the making of this <hi>chain.</hi> Fifthly, I ſhall tell you, that we have great cauſe to bleſſe GOD, for breaking this <hi>chain.</hi> And, laſtly, With all ſubmiſſion and reverence to the KING, his Commiſſioner's GRACE, and this High Court of PARLIAMENT. I ſhall make bold to ſay, that GOD is calling at your hands to make a fourfold <hi>chain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As to our <hi>condition</hi> of late theſe many years by gone, we were in a <hi>chain,</hi> we were brought and kept for many years, under a moſt baſe <hi>Slavery</hi> and <hi>Bondage,</hi> we were Slaves to Slaves, we were in a <hi>chain</hi> in all theſe reſpects, whereof I ſpoke in the Explication of the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, In a <hi>chain,</hi> becauſe we were reſtrained and deprived of our National <hi>Liberty,</hi> a yoke of <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> was faſt wreathed about our <hi>Necks:</hi> we had not power to act in any of our Publick <hi>Intereſts</hi> or <hi>Concernments,</hi> all our Civil Power and Authority taken away; yea, the Fountain of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er under GOD, taken away, the KING himſelf: our <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> razed to the foundation, our Civil and Criminal <hi>Courts</hi> made to run out of the right <hi>Channel,</hi> into a ſtrang and new fancied <hi>Commonwealth: Strangers</hi> ruled over us, and ſome temporizing <hi>Complyers</hi> of our own <hi>Land,</hi> were larg worſe than <hi>Sir angers,</hi> ſuch as our <hi>Sequeſtrators.</hi> We were in a <hi>chain</hi> alſo, in reference to our Church <hi>State,</hi> our Church <hi>Judicatories</hi> interrupted, hindered to proceed in their juſt and lawful <hi>Buſineſſes,</hi> the General <hi>Affembly</hi> raiſed by <hi>Sword-men,</hi> a juſt judgement on the Church for our too much medling in Sword matters; ſo we were in a <hi>chain</hi> for want of our native <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Freedom.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50069:10"/>
            <p>Secondly, We were in a <hi>chain,</hi> becauſe our <hi>condition</hi> was ſad and comfortleſſe, we might have weep'd as the <hi>Jews</hi> did in their <hi>captivity,</hi> when they ſate by the Rivers of <hi>Babylon.</hi> And I am ſure, there was not any, that had a true <hi>Scots</hi> heart in their <hi>Breaſt,</hi> or the ſpirit of a man within them, or the true fear of GOD in their <hi>Hearts:</hi> none in <hi>Scotland,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſorne unnatural <hi>Monſters,</hi> and Treacherous active <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliers,</hi> but it pierced their hearts through, to be chained in ſuch a baſe <hi>Bondage</hi> as we were in for many years. Tell me, what <hi>Honeſt, Godly,</hi> or <hi>Loyal</hi> heart in <hi>Scotland</hi> could ceaſe from bleeding, when they heard of that <hi>Woful, Cruel, Bloody, Treacherous, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nparalelled,</hi> and eternally to be <hi>Anathematized blow,</hi> in ſtriking off that moſt <hi>Pious, Glorious, Innocent, Sweet</hi> KINGS <hi>Head,</hi> the beſt KING amongſt the ſons of men. O <hi>Bloody Traitors! Traitors</hi> that plotted it, acted it, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it. So we were in a <hi>chain,</hi> for our condition was ſad and comfortleſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We were in a <hi>chain;</hi> becauſe our condition, was <hi>Reproachful,</hi> and <hi>Diſgraceful:</hi> We were but a laughing-ſtock to our <hi>Conquerours,</hi> the object of their <hi>contempt</hi> and <hi>ſcorn,</hi> they did in effect but Jeer us, even the civileſt of them, and they had no other cauſe; for they might have eaſily percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the one half of us, cutting the others <hi>Throat.</hi> I know not, if any Story of <hi>Scotland</hi> holds out, that ever this <hi>Land,</hi> was brought under a more <hi>diſgraceful</hi> and <hi>contemptible</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We were in a <hi>chain</hi> theſe many years, before this bleſſed <hi>Revolution;</hi> becauſe we were under many ſad and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable <hi>Burthens.</hi> Who can tell ſince the righteous <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of this <hi>Land</hi> began to be ſhaken, and the KING'S juſt <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> was moſt unjuſtly and rebelliouſly wreaſted out of his <hi>Royal Hands,</hi> and ſince that Antient and Equal <hi>Government</hi> was razed by <hi>Traitors, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,</hi> what a vaſt, incredible Treaſure of <hi>Money,</hi> hath been drained from this poor <hi>Nation?</hi> Have we not found, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50069:10"/>our late <hi>Rulers,</hi> and that fancied <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> our late pretended <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and theſe <hi>Traitorous, Bloody <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> their little finger heavier, than many of our KINGS <hi>Loyns</hi> were, for many Ages and Generations? And any <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> which the <hi>Land</hi> lyeth yet under, was occaſioned and brought in by <hi>Rebels, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers,</hi> and <hi>Tyrants,</hi> and let them be blamed for it ſo long as it ſhall continue.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, We were in a <hi>chain;</hi> becauſe theſe that kept us in <hi>Bondage,</hi> had a purpoſe that we ſhould never eſcape, and therefore they made our <hi>chain</hi> heavy and ſtrong: What were our <hi>Citadels,</hi> but as ſo many <hi>chains</hi> of Iron, to have kept this <hi>Land</hi> in a perpetual <hi>Slavery?</hi> But I proceed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing in the <hi>Application</hi> is, Who was it that made this <hi>chain?</hi> I cannot in this condeſcend on <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,</hi> although ſomething might be ſaid to this <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> which, it may be, a little piece of time will diſcover. I ſhall hold out ſome <hi>Generals:</hi> and as I ſaid of the <hi>Jews chain</hi> and <hi>captivity,</hi> ſo do I ſay of <hi>Scotlands</hi> late <hi>chain</hi> and <hi>Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, GOD made this <hi>chain</hi> for us. as a Juſt <hi>Judge,</hi> to puniſh us for playing <hi>Jeſhurun's</hi> part, in kicking off our Juſt <hi>Maſter,</hi> and moſt <hi>Gracious</hi> KING of eternal me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is not improbable that ſeveral <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nnatural, Treacherous</hi> and <hi>Perfidious Monſters</hi> amongſt our ſelves, of each <hi>Rank,</hi> have had a <hi>hand</hi> in making the <hi>chain</hi> of our <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> and in helping to wreath it about our <hi>Necks,</hi> about the <hi>Necks</hi> of all <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the <hi>Land:</hi> about the <hi>Necks</hi> of our <hi>Nobles, Barons, Burrows, Miniſtry, Commons,</hi> that ſo they might rule all, and carry all at their pleaſure, like petty <hi>Princes,</hi> and petty <hi>Popes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, That ſtrong <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>bondage,</hi> was made and wreathed faſt about our <hi>Necks,</hi> by a rebellious <hi>Faction</hi> of <hi>Sectaries;</hi> for it is far from our thoughts to impute that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion to the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> but to a <hi>Bloody</hi> and <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50069:11"/>Faction of <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> which kept theſe own <hi>Nation</hi> and Ours both in a <hi>chain of bondage.</hi> In a word, the <hi>ſpirit</hi> that moved moſt <hi>ſtrongly</hi> and <hi>powerfully</hi> in making our <hi>chain,</hi> and putting it about our <hi>Necks,</hi> was a <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, Rebellion, Sectariſm,</hi> a <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>Madneſſe,</hi> of <hi>Deluſion, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery</hi> and <hi>Hypocriſic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing in the <hi>Application,</hi> was the <hi>Cauſes</hi> wherefore the LORD ſuffered this ſad <hi>chain</hi> of our <hi>bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> to be wreathed about our <hi>Necks.</hi> In a word, beſide theſe common <hi>Sins</hi> which reigneth through all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Atheiſm, Swearing, Profanity, Drunkenneſſe, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Barreneſſe under the Goſpel,</hi> &amp;c. This <hi>Land</hi> was defiled with theſe particular <hi>Sins,</hi> contained in the <hi>Text,</hi> that is, with <hi>Bloody Crimes</hi> and <hi>Violence,</hi> and that in all theſe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects,</hi> whereof I did ſpeak in the <hi>Explication</hi> of the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, This <hi>Land</hi> was defiled with much <hi>Innocent Blood,</hi> by an unjuſt <hi>War,</hi> by riſing up againſt the KING, a <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> inconſiſtant with ſound <hi>Divinity,</hi> againſt all <hi>Orthodox Doctrine:</hi> a <hi>practice</hi> contrary to <hi>Scripture,</hi> contrary to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Antient Church,</hi> and their <hi>practice</hi> contrary to the <hi>Confeſsion</hi> of <hi>Faith: No King upon the account of his Intellectuals, Morals, or Religion, being to be ſuſpended from the exerciſe of his Government, or denied ſubmiſsion too, by his Subjects.</hi> How many mournful <hi>Widows</hi> and <hi>Fatherleſſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans,</hi> have our late <hi>civil,</hi> or rather <hi>incivil VVars</hi> made in <hi>Scotland?</hi> How many poor <hi>creatures</hi> have been ſnatched away perforce, from their <hi>weeping VVives,</hi> and poor <hi>Babies,</hi> and ſent out to be <hi>Souldiers,</hi> that knew not how to handle a <hi>Sword</hi> nor <hi>Arms?</hi> what could theſe do but be cut down like <hi>Beaſts?</hi> And doth not the <hi>Blood</hi> of theſe poor <hi>creatures</hi> cry to GOD for <hi>Vengeance,</hi> againſt <hi>Rebels, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers</hi> and <hi>Tyrants?</hi> Is not the <hi>Land</hi> defiled with much <hi>lunocent Blood</hi> by moſt <hi>unjuſt</hi> and <hi>cruel Sentences</hi> on <hi>Benches?</hi> Is not the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50069:11"/>
               <hi>Land</hi> defiled with much <hi>Innocent Blood</hi> upon <hi>Scaffolds?</hi> How many in <hi>Britain</hi> have been forced to lay down their <hi>Heads</hi> to the <hi>Block,</hi> within theſe few years of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie,</hi> and that for their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Fidelity</hi> to their <hi>Juſt</hi> and <hi>Native</hi> KING? Hath not as <hi>Noble,</hi> yea, the moſt <hi>Noble Blood</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland been ſhed on Scaffolds?</hi> And which no <hi>Story</hi> can parallel, and which none that feareth GOD indeed, or any faithful <hi>Subject,</hi> can ſpeak of, but with <hi>Horror, ſad hearts,</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> in their <hi>Eyes,</hi> was not the <hi>Royal Blood</hi> of that <hi>Bleſſed Martyr</hi> KING <hi>CHARLES</hi> the 1, of <hi>Eternal Memory,</hi> Spilt on a <hi>Scaffold,</hi> in the Famous <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> in the view of many Thouſands of his <hi>Dear, Loyal, Weeping Subjects,</hi> who had no <hi>Power</hi> for the time, to deliver that <hi>Innocent Lamb,</hi> from the teeth of theſe <hi>Bloody Cannibals, Dogs,</hi> yea, <hi>Devils Incarnat?</hi> Thus was the <hi>Land</hi> defiled with <hi>bloody crimes.</hi> And was it not full of <hi>Violence</hi> alſo, full of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs, Falſhood, Deceit, Cheating, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtice, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion</hi> and <hi>Robery,</hi> defiled with <hi>Violence</hi> of all ſorts? What <hi>Oppreſſion, Injuſtice</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> was there by <hi>Blind bands, Loan Money,</hi> or rather taking mens <hi>Means,</hi> and Impriſoning their <hi>Perſons,</hi> Forcing of <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and ſeverall things of that nature?</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth thing in the <hi>Application</hi> was, To Exhort all <hi>Eſtates</hi> in the <hi>Land,</hi> both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> to repent and mourn before GOD, for our <hi>Acceſſion</hi> to the making of that <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>Bondage,</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> wherewith this poor <hi>Land</hi> hath been fettered theſe many years by gone: It will never be well with <hi>Scotland,</hi> neither will GOD be fully pacified with us, and turn away his <hi>Anger</hi> wholly from us, till all <hi>Ranks</hi> of people in <hi>Scotland, Nobles, Gentry, Burrows,:</hi> And in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, til we of the <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> come to an ingenious <hi>confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> of our <hi>Acceſſion</hi> to the making of the <hi>Chain.</hi> Shall we charge this on others, and wipe our own mouth like the <hi>Whore?</hi> No, we are us <hi>Guilty</hi> as any, and GOD will extort a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> from us, whether we will or no.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50069:12"/>
            <p n="5">5. Let us bleſs GOD who hath broken that <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation</hi> and <hi>Bondage,</hi> wherewith this poor <hi>Land,</hi> was ſo long and faſt tyed: by reducing and reſtoring, our <hi>Native</hi> KING, to his juſt <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Prerogatives,</hi> and by reſtoring to us, the <hi>Liberty, Freedom</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments.</hi> Let us admire and adore the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of GOD, who upon a ſudden, <hi>befooled</hi> the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Zoan,</hi> the great <hi>Wits,</hi> the cunning <hi>Achitophels</hi> and <hi>Matchavels</hi> of <hi>Brittain.</hi> Let us admire the LORDS <hi>Out-witting, Over-topping,</hi> and <hi>Over-turning</hi> all the <hi>Cabinet Councels</hi> of that <hi>Perfidious</hi> and <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Cabal.</hi> I ſay again, it is a duty well be-coming, this High and Honorable <hi>Court</hi> of PARLIAMENT, to bleſs GOD from your hearts, for breaking the <hi>chain</hi> of our <hi>bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> by reducing and reſtoring Our <hi>Native</hi> KING, to his juſt <hi>Rights, Royal Dignity</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> after ſuch a ſad and long <hi>Exile,</hi> by a pack of <hi>falſe, greedy, ambitious, hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, cruel, Bloody Murtherers</hi> and <hi>Traitors,</hi> who called them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>Saints,</hi> and that in deſpight of all the <hi>Enemies</hi> of the <hi>Royal Family</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> who were not few. And if any have yet a Bone in their <hi>Stomack,</hi> againſt the KING, His <hi>Family</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> time will try; <hi>for it is not all Gold that Gliſters:</hi> Mal-contents will diſcover themſelves one way or another: For fairded <hi>Loyalty</hi> will ſoon be rubbed off, when occaſion offereth. But let <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Happineſs</hi> attend all that are cordially <hi>Loyal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. To cloſe, Let it not ſeem <hi>Preſumption</hi> nor <hi>Vanity,</hi> in ſuch a poor weak man as I am, to ſay, that in my humble o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, GOD is calling upon KING and PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT to do two things. Firſt, To break off all <hi>unjuſt, illegall</hi> and <hi>Tyrannical chains,</hi> which wicked and evil men have made, and faſtened about the Neck of this poor <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> and in this his MAJESTIES <hi>Commiſſioner,</hi> and this Honorable <hi>Court</hi> of PARLIAMENT have made a very conſiderable and noble <hi>Progreſs,</hi> to their eternal me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. Secondly, I humbly conceive that GOD calleth
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50069:12"/>to KING and PARLIAMENT to make a <hi>Chain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, A <hi>Chain</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> for all ſuch, who upon clear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences ſhall be found guilty, of the <hi>Plotting, Contriving,</hi> or <hi>Acting</hi> in that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nparalelled Murther</hi> of the late KING, the <hi>betraying,</hi> or <hi>ſelling</hi> his MAJESTY, and the <hi>Ancient Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of this <hi>Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, A <hi>Chain</hi> of new <hi>Laws,</hi> or the reviving of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Laws,</hi> if they can be by more ſevere and terrible <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> for preventing the like <hi>Treachery, Diſloyalty</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation</hi> in time coming: <hi>Ex malis moribus oriuntur bonae leges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, A <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>Regulation</hi> in reference to <hi>Church-Government:</hi> Remember my <hi>words,</hi> it is the <hi>regulation</hi> of <hi>Church-Government</hi> by <hi>Civil Authority</hi> I ſpeak of. I mean, that <hi>Church-Government</hi> be not ſuffered by the <hi>Civil Power,</hi> the KING and PARLIAMENT, to run without its own <hi>Channel,</hi> nor to be excentrick to <hi>Church Matters,</hi> but that it may be kepet within its own <hi>Banks.</hi> I ſhall not uſe that <hi>Argument</hi> which ſome calls a <hi>Fallacy,</hi> that is, to reaſon from the faults of <hi>Governours,</hi> againſt the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> from the outſtretching of a <hi>Government,</hi> to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning of a <hi>Government,</hi> and yet that <hi>Argument</hi> was made uſe of in <hi>Anno</hi> 1638. But I may very lawfully and juſtly without <hi>Fallacy,</hi> in all equity, <hi>Argue</hi> from the outſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>Government,</hi> or from the abuſe of it, to the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation</hi> of it, and putting of it within its own <hi>Channel.</hi> I think, that all <hi>Church-Government</hi> ſhould be ſo Regulated by the KING and PARLIAMENT, that it be not ſuffered to cope with the Supream <hi>Authority</hi> of a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> much leſs to counteract thereto, leaſt of all to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top the Supream <hi>Authority,</hi> that is <hi>Popiſh.</hi> I think, that <hi>Church-Government</hi> ſhould be ſo regulated, that there be not in one <hi>Kingdom,</hi> two <hi>Supream Coordinat Powers</hi> to claſh one upon another, and to diſtract and rent the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50069:13"/>of the <hi>Subjects,</hi> ſo that they know not whom to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey: Whether the KING and the Supream <hi>Civil Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> or the Supream <hi>Church Power?</hi> Did not the <hi>Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of 1648. ſpeak out this too clearly, when the PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAMENT ordered one thing, and the <hi>Church</hi> the contrary? This ſhould be remeaded by the KING and PARLIAMENT. I am no <hi>Statſ-man,</hi> yet I take it to be beyond an Ordinary <hi>Wit,</hi> to make two <hi>Coordinat Supream Powers</hi> in one <hi>Land,</hi> conſiſting with the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Peace thereof, eſpecially a <hi>Nation</hi> that is <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall.</hi> I conceive, that too many lay a wrong <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,</hi> in reference to this <hi>matter;</hi> whereupon they build wrong <hi>Superſtructures;</hi> for they look upon the <hi>State, Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> as upon two ſeverall, diſtinct, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent <hi>Bodies,</hi> while as they are not two <hi>Bodies,</hi> but two <hi>parts</hi> of one and the ſame <hi>Politick Body,</hi> under one <hi>Chief</hi> and <hi>Supream Civil Governour:</hi> And although the <hi>Supream Civil Authority</hi> ought not to meddle immediatly with <hi>Things</hi> meerly <hi>Spiritual,</hi> Such as the <hi>Preaching</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> Adminiſtration of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the <hi>Keys,</hi> theſe things being committed by CHRIST to the <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> yet it is proper for the <hi>Supream Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> to meddle with <hi>Things</hi> that are <hi>Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> to ſee the <hi>Church</hi> in His <hi>Dominions</hi> rightly <hi>Conſtituted,</hi> and rightly <hi>Governed:</hi> For in reference to the external <hi>Regiment</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>Supream Gubernative Power</hi> is in the <hi>Supream Magiſtrate:</hi> And therefore the Reformation of <hi>Religion,</hi> without the <hi>conſent,</hi> much leſs contrary to the <hi>Will</hi> of a <hi>Supream Chriſtian Magiſtrate,</hi> hath no warrantable <hi>Precedent</hi> in GODS <hi>Word;</hi> but the very contrary is holden out there. See <hi>Deuter. chap.</hi> 29. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10, 11, 12. <hi>Joſh. chap.</hi> 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. 2 <hi>King. chap.</hi> 23. 2 <hi>Chron. chap.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8.12. 2 <hi>Chron. chap.</hi> 29. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.10. 2 <hi>Chron. chap.</hi> 34. <hi>verſ.</hi> 31.32. <hi>Ezra chap.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.5. compared with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50069:13"/>
               <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. And ſeverall other places of <hi>Scripture</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Chief <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> conourreth; or rather according to his <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> goeth before the people: But we find no where in <hi>Scripture,</hi> the people reforming, without the conourrence of the <hi>Supream Magiſtrate,</hi> even in the times of their worſt <hi>Kings.</hi> And any who will deny that it ſo, in the beginning of <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtracy,</hi> will ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ignorants in <hi>Antiquity.</hi> And is it not more ſuitable and agreeable to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> more for the <hi>Honor, Safety,</hi> and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of a <hi>Church,</hi> and the <hi>Government</hi> thereof, and for the advancement of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> in a <hi>Land,</hi> that the <hi>Church</hi> depend rather upon the KING and Supream <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> than upon <hi>popularity,</hi> the natural <hi>product</hi> whereof is <hi>coufuſion</hi> and <hi>tumult,</hi> as the <hi>breathing</hi> and <hi>wind</hi> of <hi>factions</hi> and <hi>ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Spirits</hi> bloweth upon theſe <hi>waters?</hi> It is my hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble opinion, that there ought to be ſuch a <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> put about <hi>Church-Government,</hi> as it ſhall not be <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> for the <hi>Church</hi> to preſcribe <hi>reſtrictions</hi> and <hi>limitations</hi> to the KING, before his admiſſion to the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of his <hi>Royal Power;</hi> ſuch a <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>Regulation,</hi> as it may not be <hi>lawfull</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi> to declare againſt the KING, to ſtate <hi>Quarrels</hi> in matters of <hi>War,</hi> to purge <hi>Armies,</hi> and leaſt of all, to exclude the KINGS <hi>Intereſt</hi> out of the ſtate of the <hi>Quarrel,</hi> to force the KING to ſubſcribe <hi>Papers</hi> and <hi>Declarations,</hi> contrary to his will; ſuch a <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>Regulation,</hi> that it ſhall not be lawfull for <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> to proteſt againſt the <hi>Magiſtrates Lawfull Power,</hi> in raiſing all fenſible <hi>Parſons</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> for the juſt and neceſſary <hi>Defence</hi> thereof, and calling that neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Duty</hi> a <hi>Sin,</hi> and a conjunction with the <hi>Malignant Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi> a <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> inconſiſtant with the Safety of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Nation:</hi> a <hi>Proteſtation</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> to be abhorred by all <hi>Modeſt</hi> and <hi>Loyal-men:</hi> Clearly contrary to the <hi>Law</hi> of GOD, of <hi>Nature,</hi> of <hi>Nations:</hi> A <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> never heard of ſince the beginning of the <hi>VVorld,</hi> in any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:50069:14"/>
               <hi>Story, Sacred</hi> or <hi>Profane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> A <hi>Principle</hi> which ought to be well adverted, that the like may be preveened in time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: A <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> to be <hi>Stigmatized,</hi> as well as the <hi>Remonſtrauce;</hi> Such a <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>Regulation,</hi> as may lay a <hi>Reſtraint</hi> upon <hi>Miniſters,</hi> from ſtarting or venting <hi>Queſtions, Principles</hi> or <hi>Tenets,</hi> deſtructive to the <hi>Supream Civil Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> or which may have any tendency to unſettle <hi>Authority,</hi> and to ſhake the <hi>Peace</hi> of a <hi>Nation;</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of oppoſing and reſiſting of KINGS by their own <hi>Subjects,</hi> through Force of <hi>Arms:</hi> the crying down the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Actings</hi> of a Free PARLIAMENT: <hi>Popular Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> the laying too much <hi>Streſſe</hi> upon any <hi>Humane Draught</hi> whatſoever, as if it were the <hi>Baſis</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> or making any thing the rule of <hi>Faith, VVorſhip,</hi> and <hi>Religious Practice,</hi> but the <hi>VVord</hi> of GOD. All which may, and ought to be done with due reſpect and tenderneſſe too, and preſervation of the <hi>Juſt Power, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> according to the <hi>Holy Scripture,</hi> taken in its <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> and <hi>Genuine Senſe,</hi> and according to the <hi>Antient Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick Practice,</hi> and for the advancement of <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, I humbly conceive, GOD calleth KING and PARLIAMENT, to make a <hi>chain</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> which may gird the <hi>Laws</hi> about, and make them effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all by a vigorous <hi>Execution;</hi> for a <hi>Law</hi> without <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,</hi> is but a <hi>Bee</hi> without a <hi>Sting:</hi> And there can be no <hi>Law</hi> really executed, without <hi>Power.</hi> And therefore theſe who did wreſt the <hi>Militia</hi> out of the <hi>Late Martyred</hi> KING'S hands, did in effect deſtroy all <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> by robbing the KING of the <hi>Sword,</hi> the choiſeſt <hi>Flowre</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> of the <hi>Crown. Neceſſity, Duty, Safety,</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Quiet</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> the putting <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> to a lively <hi>Execution,</hi> calleth for <hi>Power,</hi> that ſo <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Profanity, Violence, Robbery,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſsion</hi> in the <hi>Land, Schiſm</hi> in the <hi>Church, Ruptures</hi> in the <hi>State, Mutinies, Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50069:14"/>Plottings,</hi> and <hi>Contrivances</hi> to involve the <hi>Nation</hi> in new <hi>Troubles</hi> by Mal-contents, may be timely preveened and kept under; for though the face of the <hi>VVaters</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſmooth for the preſent, there is ſome ſtirrngs at the <hi>Bottom,</hi> by theſe who have put on a preſent <hi>Mask</hi> of <hi>Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but are ready to pull off, when they can ſee their <hi>Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</hi> I crave <hi>Pardon</hi> for my boldneſſe, in offering my <hi>raſh Thoughts</hi> to His MAJESTIES <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> GRACE, and to his <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Honourable Court,</hi> in matters of ſo great <hi>Concernment;</hi> but I may ſay, I do it in all <hi>humility,</hi> and from a principle of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> to my SOVERAIGN the KING, to the <hi>Country,</hi> and to my <hi>Mother Church,</hi> let <hi>Men</hi> conſtruct it as they liſt, and ſo. I end, Giving <hi>Glory</hi> to the FATHER, SON, and HOLY GHOST. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>GOD SAVE THE KING.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
